<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Git | Donovan Whitworth]]></title>
  <link href="http://dwhitworth.github.io/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dwhitworth.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-18T22:26:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://dwhitworth.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Donovan Whitworth]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[donovan.whitworth@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[git stash]]></title>
    <link href="http://dwhitworth.github.io/blog/2014/02/23/git-stash/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-23T18:46:06-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dwhitworth.github.io/blog/2014/02/23/git-stash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During this weekend&rsquo;s hackathon, our team split up duties when we were not pair programming. With over 50 issues, 90 commits and <!-- more -->30 branches, this means we had a s**t-ton of pull requests, code-review and merging, in our effort to apply best practices for version control.</p>

<p>When we had merge conflicts, Git suggested we stash our changes, pull down the most recent changes, then merge our branch and resolve merge issues before pushing.</p>

<p>Great, but I had no idea what git stash was.</p>

<p>Well, in plain language, git warns you that if you pull a branch, you better be ready for it to overwrite everything you&rsquo;ve just done unless you take certain steps:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Discard your changes: You could use <code>$ git clean</code> or <code>$ git reset –hard</code> to do this, this would make all your local changes disappear.</p></li>
<li><p>Ignore your changes: <code>$ git checkout</code> would keep any changes you made locally that do not conflict with the incoming merge, but you will lose any local changes that do have merge conflicts.</p></li>
<li><p>Set your changes aside: <code>$ git stash</code> hides your local changes so you can pull down the most recent master, then &lsquo;unstash&rsquo; your changes and resolve merge issues locally.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>So, here is what my normal workflow looked like if I came across a merge conflict:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ git stash
$ git pull
$ git stash apply
</code></p>

<p>You can stash multiple times, but it can get pretty messy. If you have multiple stashes, type <code>$ git list</code> to get a list of your stashes, the output would look something like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
stash@{0}: WIP on master: 049d078 added the index file
stash@{1}: WIP on master: c264051... Revert "added file_size"
stash@{2}: WIP on master: 21d80a5... added number to log
</code></p>

<p>If this is the case, simply using <code>$ git stash</code> would only apply the most recent stash, so if you wanted to apply a different commit, you would type <code>$ git stash apply stash@{2}</code>, or whatever number corresponds to the stash you want to apply.</p>

<p>Bye for now :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
